[Music]
[Applause]
so being the glute guy i get asked all
the time
brett what's the best way to train the
glutes and the answer is
you need to be doing the rule of thirds
so i first wrote about the rule of
thirds on february 9
2018 and here's how it came to be i
noticed i was answering questions very
similarly
you know back in the day in like 2009 i
came out with
this vector terminology so i i noticed
that some glute exercises are
vertical in nature like the vector is
coming downward relative to the body
so those are things like your squats
your deadlifts
your step ups bulgarian split squats
lunges uh you know different types of
deadlifts like
romanian stiff leg deadlifts good
mornings they're all vertical hip
extension exercises
and then some exercise our horizontal
invector relative to the body
these are your hip thrusts your glute
bridges your frog pumps your back
extensions your cable pull throws
your reverse hypers uh your kickbacks
your
quadruped hip extensions these exercises
are amazing for glute development but
they're all horizontal and then the
final category is kind of like lateral
rotary and these
are like your abduction and extra
rotation movements these are your
you know seated hip abduction machine
your
standing cable hip abduction all the
stuff you do with bands like your
lateral band walks
and basically all the abduction and
external rotation exercise which there
aren't many good
hip external rotation rotation exercise
but the the one we do most is the cable
cuff hip external rotation so people
would ask me how much should i do of
each and i'd say
around a third of each you know a
30-year exercise should be
horizontal a third vertical a third
lateral rotate then i'd say the same
thing to load people really like how
often should i go
heavy how often should i go light health
and medium and i'd say run a third
like go heavy some of the time some of
the time moderate some of the time light
uh you know heavy would be like in the
one to five rep range
moderate in the six to 15 and light in
the 16 to like 100 rep range usually 16
to 30 though and then finally
with effort you know people would say
how often should i train to failure and
i'd say
well probably around a 30-year set
should be taken to failure
and then like a third should be a couple
reps shy of failure and then a third
not even close to failure like maybe 10
reps shy so
i started noticing i was given similar
answers to these questions so
i developed what i call the rule of
thirds as it pertains to glute training
so i kind of just explained the rule of
thirds but i'll reiterate
uh the rule of thirds has three
components and we're going to use an
example here of
someone training three days a week okay
say they train on monday wednesday
friday they train glutes
and they do 12 sets each day each
training day so
12 sets three times a week would be 36
total sets
per week for glutes okay so you do 36
sets a week for glutes
then around 12 of your sets should be
horizontal hip extension exercises 12 of
your sets should be vertical hip
extensions
and 12 of them would be lateral rotary
glute exercises okay
around 12 of your sets would be heavy
around 12 sets moderate
around 12 cents light you'd take around
12 sets to failure
12 sets a couple reps shia failure and
12 sets nowhere close to failure well
what's nice is this this type of
training lends itself well
like for the three categories well let
me explain so
let's say you do lateral lateral rotary
exercise like hip abduction
no one does a one rep max seated hip
abduction
you know you're not gonna do a one rep
max cable standing hip abduction either
those exercises lend themselves well to
like the 20-ish rep range you know
horizontal hip extension exercises are
typically
higher reps too you know yes you can do
heavy hip thrusts but
a lot of times with like frog pumps and
kickbacks you're doing sets of like
you know at least 12
uh but even with frog pumps up to 100
reps and then vertical
tend to lend themselves better to
heavier weight like yes you of course
you could do sets of 20 with like squats
or lunges but
those exercises lend themselves to heavy
training you know closer to barrier or
things like squats deadlifts
uh and even like bulgarian split squats
you know
you typically don't do a one remax but
you might do a a heavy set of six
six to 12 or something like that so the
training
does make sense if you do all of them
you tend to it tends to balance itself
out well anyway now the point of the
rule of thirds is not to become
obsessive compulsive about it
is to just have this in mind when you
design your programs and when you do
your workouts
am i in good balance let's say all you
did was vertical hip extension exercises
super heavy to failure how many heavy
sets to failure could you do of like
deadlifts and squats and walking lunges
i can't recover from those very easily
those beat you up a lot more they're
very taxing on the body
now in contrast if you do moderate
weight horizontal hip extensions they
don't beat you up too bad you know
sets of 12 reps on the hip thrust you
know
back extensions for 20 reps things like
that and then abduction movements i
always joke around that they're
penalty free volume meaning you know
they don't beat you up much the next day
you're not like oh my god i can't move
i'm so beat up systemically from those
abduction movements
so back when i joined the industry the
only thing that was popular was vertical
and back then all the bodybuilders would
say you've got to
train every set to failure now we know
from the research that you don't have
in fact doing so taking every set to
fair
is counterproductive and lateral rotary
exercise lend themselves well to the
not training close to failure category
because you know you stop when it burns
but if someone had a gun to your head
you could probably get 10 more reps
oh god it burns oh
oh one more one more
oh okay that was failure that was
failure
[__] who the [__] are you [__] do
ten more right now
[__] you shoot me [__] do 10 more
right now
now what can you expect if you adhere to
the rule of thirds
well first of all you're going to fully
develop all the regions of the glutes
you know the gluteus maximus has an
upper and lower subdivision and the
glute medius and minimus both have
anter and middle and posterior regions
so they'll all get maximally developed
on this system you're also going to
fully develop the fast and slow twitch
muscle fibers now the research is kind
of mixed on this in fact
we did a study with uh with brad
schoenfeld's group and it did not
really support that a variety of rep
ranges was that much better than just
doing like medium reps but in theory
heavier weight is gonna build the fast
twitch fibers a little bit better
and then the higher reps would build the
slow twitch fibers a little bit this way
it leaves no stone unturned you're also
gonna hit the glutes from every angle
and vector
and you're gonna perform the three main
joint actions of the gluteus maximus you
know hip extension
hip external rotation and hip abduction
and this way you're gonna maximize
functional transference to life and
sport so if you're looking for
performance benefits you know the glutes
are tri-planar in nature you know
picture swinging a baseball bat you know
you're loaded up
you're leaning into this hip and then
you explode well when you explode
you're you're actually in hip flexion
and you're you're not in full abduction
and you're you know kind of like not
externally rotated
and when you swing the bat you're going
to notice
simultaneously you perform hip extension
hip abduction and hip external rotation
at the same time
so it makes sense if you're looking for
performance gains
to perform all those actions in the gym
and finally you're going to be able to
tolerate higher workloads in the gym
without
developing you know excessive systemic
or local fatigue you know the vertical
hip extension exercises beat you up
systemically the most they also create
the most muscle damage they also hit the
lower glutes the best the horizontal hip
extension exercise they don't beat you
up as much
and they probably maximize upper and
lower glute development
and then the abduction movements are you
know they're more
targeted they don't develop a ton of
muscle damage either
but they develop the upper glutes more
again the point of the rule of thirds
you don't want to become obsessive
compulsive about it
and like analyze every month's training
program make sure it's perfectly fit
like with my booty by brett program
sometimes we
prioritize the squat well you're
probably going to do more vertical hip
extension exercise that month sometimes
we prioritize the hip thrust you're
probably going to do a little more
uh horizontal and maybe more moderate
reps
that that month and that's fine the
point is to be thinking about this and
throughout the year you should be pretty
balanced
so if you want nice glutes follow the
rule of thirds
and watch your glutes grow now if you
like this video
please make sure to give it a thumbs up
make sure to leave a comment
if you have questions i'm trying to be
better at answering them and make sure
you're subscribed to my channel
i'm going to be trying to come out with
regular weekly content
that's the main goal for 2021 so i've
got a lot more good stuff to come
now if this video intrigued you and you
would like to train
under my system using my principles then
i invite you to click on the link below
and subscribe to booty by brett and join
the thousands of other happy members
who are seeing amazing results